

Martin Stuart Dawson

Profile

An experienced CRM Director with emphasis on data-led marketing solutions with strong commercial acumen. Results orientated with a consistent high drive for success but ever mindful of team ethics. With a breadth of business and direct marketing skills, an individual who can thrive in different organisations.

Work experience

July 2019 to date – Field Consultant, Marketing (Contact Strategy) Dell Technologies (www.dell.co.uk)

Dell is an American multinational computer technology company that develops, sells, repairs, and supports computers and related products and services.

Recruited to manage UK Consumer and Small Business Contact Strategy.

- Reporting to the Global Head of Contact Strategy, this role centres around the overall
 contact strategy between Dell UK and its customers: Creating target universes or
 campaigns for Email, Direct Mail, Digital Audiences and Outbound Telemarketing.
- Role includes strategy and overseeing of direct mail, email, outbound telemarketing campaigns for the UK. This encompasses everything from the data aspect with joint input into format and creative with UK Marketing team.
- Successfully delivered YoY growth FY2020 Revenue (\$): +72% B2C Consumer email, +33% Small Business Email, +22% Small Business Telemarketing. Combined growth total c\$5m
- Successfully oversaw the transition from an external Marketing Services Provider to inhouse. Specifically, aspects of database and marketing tech transition, campaign planning, campaign execution, parallel runs, QC etc

May 2016 to March 2019 – Senior Strategy & Planning Manager, MarketReach, Royal Mail (www.mailmen.co.uk)

MarketReach is the B2B marketing arm of the Royal Mail. Its objective is the championing of the letterbox and the value it brings to both brands and consumers alike. MarketReach offers UK industry free unparalleled support in how to maximise mail media from strategic level insight to tactical advice and best practice in campaigns irrespective of postal operator used.

- Reporting to the Head of Strategy & Planning is a multi-discipline role with one part
 managing the in-house Media and Data Planning resources to answer the 500+ briefs
 from brands and agencies in their use of mail in a multichannel world. 2018 saw
 record Planning support of brands advertising mail sales (£78m) with briefs varying
 from Cases for Mail in Digital World to customer journey workshops integrating mail
 with digital in types of communications
- In addition, was lead on various client or channel business development projects such as: Acquisition and Retention strategy best practice, marketing data strategy and performance, loyalty, consumer behaviour plus identified, proposed and played a major role in the 2018 launch of Partially Addressed mail.
- Also managed relationships and contracts with suppliers & some agencies including Ebiquity, IPA, Kantar, Mintel and Nielsen. Since taking over have saved over £50K in reshaping more efficient contracts.
- Have subject matter expertise in areas of data protection including GDPR. As a result lead the MarketReach marketing campaign 'GDPRmailwise' relating to GDPR including printed guide, events, social and digital campaign which has resulted in over £10m in incremental mail revenue

Oct 14 to Apr 2016 (www.dixonscarphonegroup.com)

Dixons Carphone is Europe's leading specialist electrical and telecommunications retailer and services company. Encompassing Currys PC World, Carphone Warehouse, PC World Business, Dixons Travel, KnowHow, Dixons Carphone offers consumers and businesses alike the single place to research and purchase leading technology products and services from major networks.

May 15 - Apr 16 Snr CRM Analysis & Data Strategy Manager

- Role created through the merger of Dixons & Carphone CRM teams.
- A planning & strategy role with its roots in customer data leading a team of 4 analysts that defined the main communications strategy across customer types, brands and merchandise areas
- Was the main CRM lead in the combination and transformation of the Dixons and Carphone Warehouse Single Customer Views into one exceptional asset. Being the single voice of CRM in this £30m+ major project, role required defining the final outcome and providing expertise in how the data is best transformed and combined. Also included sourcing and specifying new data enrichment partner to drive up the value of the SCV to the business, increasing the breadth and depth of its value.
- In addition, the lead for a new CRM messaging platform which included writing the RFI, shortlist criteria and leading CRM decision-making through the selection process. This including gathering functional/non functional requirements and detailing requirement to successfully supporting the Project Director in the implementation with the chosen partner.

Oct 14 - May 15 - Snr Marketing Manager, CRM

- Leading an end-to-end team of 15 responsible for all main brands and supplier funded campaigns across all CRM marketing vehicles – Over 30 email deployments per week
- The CRM lead in all through-the-line campaigns, defining how CRM will play its part and following through into execution
- An expansive role which included budgeting, forecasting, planning, data strategy, contact strategy, creative, results & customer insight analysis
- From the 6m eCRM universe, achieved revenue & margin growth targets of £20m, and increased the active CRM base by 15%. This was achieved by devising and implementing a segmentation that incorporated promotional history. This reduced fatigue in consumers, increasing conversion and reducing opt outs.

Dec 13 to Oct 14 – Shopper Insights Consultant - Flixmedia Ltd (www.flixmedia.eu)

Flixmedia syndicates over 50 global consumer electronics brand's digital product content across 200+ ecommerce shopping sites in countries worldwide. Through the provision of Javascript 'INPages' and 'Minisites', brands can be assured that every product page in the world is not only on brand but contains the correct, current product information. This resulting in better consumer experience and high conversion. In turn, how consumers interacted with the content and converted is being returned to Flixmedia to further understand how consumers are engaging and responding to syndicated content

- The Shopper Insights Consultant was the client facing Director of the Shopper Insights & Optimisation team.
- This role was to interpret consumer browsing and shopping behaviour and make recommendations to brands on how to optimise their syndicated content.
- Responsibilities ranged from interpreting results to working directly with clients such as Samsung, Sony, Microsoft, Bose, Hotpoint and Dyson in how to better leverage their product content.
- Provided (first hand) new direction for these brands in how they design and layout product pages plus edits to their video's achieving up to 15% uplift in add-to-cart rates following my recommendations

June 13- Dec 13 – Solutions Development Director - Information Arts (Contract) (www.information-arts.com)

Information Arts is a leading B2B data & insight agency providing a variety of solutions including data, data planning & analytics to global, multichannel single customer views with campaign management. As part of Harte Hanks, the #1 MSP for the CiT sector, clients include Cisco, VMWare, EMC, Salesforce and Xerox

- This commercial role was to redefine the IA data provision offering and this included various product positioning and roadmap, pricing, new business strategy, marketing, social media strategy, public speaking & resource optimisation.
- Key deliverables included: Mapping the customer journey to better understand what challenges IA solves and identifying moments of truth for new clients to ensure longevity in the relationship
- Repackaging data and services suite to be more attractive and better suited to the target market
- Successfully sourced and account managed clients to define their data requirements and make recommendations for sources.
- In my tenure, delivered a revised product and service recommendation for their data solutions which drove revenues of over £500K in 3 months.

March 2003 – Jun 13 – Epsilon International - Abacus UK (www.abacusalliance.com)

o Mar 03 - Jun13 - Account Manager, Account Director, Senior Account Director, Client Services Manager and [360] Business Development Director

Abacus UK is the leading Co-Operative database for the Home Shopping Market with over 700 brands contributing to a transactional database of over 26 million consumers. The client services team is responsible for all the planning of prospect acquisition & customer data via custom built statistical models that mine the database. Roles also extend to briefing and presenting analysis and insight giving brands greater vision into customers and their shopping behaviour.

- 10 years developing from Account Executive through to Management including running a team of 5 as Client Services Manager and spearheading 'Abacus [360]' a retainer led, full service solution.
- Core role specialised in sales account management, working with analysts to define and deliver complex data strategies that mined the Abacus Co-Operative database to deliver customer acquisition and retention solutions, analysis and insight
- Recruited, developed and managed a team with combined revenue of over 70% of revenue (£5m)
- In the first year of [360] signed 4 clients to contracts worth over £1m
- Key managed clients: ASOS, Bose, Damart, Direct Wines, Joe Browns, Scotts of Stow and Thompson & Morgan providing the majority of their acquisition data plus applying Abacus techniques and data in their retention data selections.

May 2001 - March 03 CMP Europe Ltd

Recruitment Advertising Sales Executive

CMP Europe is part of United Business Media and offers a selection of high quality exhibitions for the IT industry and other information based products.

 Account Manager – Technology For Marketing (now TFM&A) and Call Centre Expo UK, Call Centre Expo Europe, The Call Centre Datafile

Jan 2000 – April 2001 Moriati Media (UK) Ltd
Direct & Digital Media Sales Recruitment Consultant
Aug 1998 – Dec 1999 MSM International Ltd (Publishing)
Deputy Advertisement Manager
Aug 1997 – July 1998 Haymarket Business Publishing Ltd

Education

1987 – 1993 Aylesbury Grammar School Bucks, UK GCSE & A-Level

- 11 GCSE's Grade A-C
- 2 A-Level General Studies & Geology

1993 – 1997 University of Plymouth, Devon, UK

• BSc (Hons) Maritime Business & Law

2008 - 2009 Institute of Direct Marketing, London, UK

Direct & Interactive Diploma in Direct Marketing

Additional Courses

 Numerous bespoke training courses on man-management, sales & consulting skills, budgeting & forecasting, direct marketing, coaching, motivation and conflict resolution.

Software Education

- Have advanced skills in all Microsoft Office packages and Jira
- Some experience with Apteco FastStats, SQL, SAS Enterprise Miner, Adobe Campaign Salesforce Marketing Cloud (and Exact Target), Epsilon Harmony, Oracle Responsys and IBM Unica